A Guide to the Edward Meeks "Pope" Gregory Papers, 1967-1995
Virginia Commonwealth University, James Branch Cabell Library
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library
Edward Meeks "Pope" Gregory Papers, 1967-1995
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library
M346
1.77 Linear Feet.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Donated to the Special Collections and Archives Department by Bob Swisher in May 2005.
Biographical Information
The Reverend Edward Meeks "Pope" Gregory (1922-1995) was a humanitarian, who fought racism and advocated racial and sexual equality long before they were widely accepted in Richmond, Virginia. Gregory is also recognized for holding the first gay marriage ceremony in Virginia, in August 1978, on the lawn of St. Peter's Church in Richmond.
Gregory, a Richmond native, attended St. Christopher's School and graduated from the University of Virginia (UVA) in 1947 with a bachelor's degree in English. He later did graduate work in English at both the University of Virginia and George Washington University. Gregory received a master of divinity degree in 1954 from Episcopal Theological Seminary in Cambridge, Massachusetts, and a doctor of ministry degree from the University of the South in 1977.
In 1955, Gregory was ordained a priest and served at St. Mark's Church in Richmond, as well as a youth adviser for the diocese the following year. In 1969, he was appointed vicar of St. Peter's, a mission on Church Hill. In break with tradition, Gregory gathered his parishioners around a carved, round altar for his services there. During the 1970s, when women were forcefully making their way into a previously all-male Episcopal priesthood, he invited an illegally ordained woman to celebrate Communion with him. Gregory served St. Peter's until 1979 when he left Richmond to become chaplain and teacher of English and Social Studies at rural Christ Church School, an Episcopal academy in Middlesex County. In 1990, he retired and returned to Richmond.
Gregory served as president of the Richmond-Petersburg Council on Human Relations and the Richmond Area Council on Human Relations. He helped to start the Daily Planet, which serves the homeless, and was also the advisor to Dignity/Integrity, a national organization with local chapters to homosexuals sponsored by his diocese and the Catholic Diocese of Richmond.
Gregory died Wednesday, January 25, 1995, in a local hospital after a brief illness. He is buried in Richmond's Hollywood Cemetery. At Gregory's request his memorial stone bears the Latin inscription, "Pontificeamus," in English, "Let us build bridges," the mission of his ministry and life.
Scope and Content
The materials in this collection range from 1967 to 1995 and include correspondence with local churches and individuals; organizational files from the Commission of Human Sexuality and the Commission on Human Relations, Dignity / Integrity; photographs; and publications that encompass gay activism at local and national levels during the 1970s.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in seven series: Series I. General Correspondence, Series II. Commission on Human Sexuality Files, Series III. Commission on Human Relations Files, Series IV. Dignity / Integrity, Series V. Miscellaneous Organizatonal Files, Series VI. Photographs, Series VII. Publications, and is highlighted by Gregory's organizational involvements.
Contents List
- General Correspondence, 1976-1991 (Box 1)
  - n.d., 1977, 1978, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - n.d., 1978, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 1976, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 1978, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 1977, 1978, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Commission on Human Sexuality Files, 1976-1978 (Box 1)
  - n.d., 1977, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - n.d., 1977, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - n.d., 1976, 1977, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Commission on Human Relations Files, 1975-1979 (Box 1)
  - n.d., 1977, 1978, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - n.d., 1975, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - 1978 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Dignity / Integrity, 1971-1981 (Box 1)
  - n.d., 1971, 1973-1979 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - n.d., 1975, 1976, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - 1975-1981 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - n.d., 1976, 1977, 1979, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - n.d., 1973-1977, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Miscellaneous Organizational Files, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Photographs, 1978, 1976 (Box 1)
  - August 1978 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - August 1978 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - August 1978 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - June 1986 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Publications, 1967-1995 (Box 1)
  - n.d., 1976-1979, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - n.d., 1977, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - n.d. (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - n.d., 1977, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - n.d., 1967, 1968, 1976-1978 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - 1976, 1978-1980 (Box 2)